[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I thought maybe you could say something about the parallels or similarities between this sort of structure of the sattva-kathānas and jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just something you've been searching for.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think the most obvious thing is to, as we've repeated a countless amount of times,
[SPEAKER_01]: In, eh... in our talks is the, eh... mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's what the common thread is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically what samādhi is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness that is properly established.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether you're mindful through, eh... through satipaṭṭhānas, mindful of your body, you can't turn that mindfulness, then, on into practice of the jhāna if you start, as Buddha said, if you start discerning the factors of the jhāna, what are the things necessary for the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why I wouldn't necessarily go, oh, this is what's similar, this is what's parallel.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like, if you have mindfulness established to the certain necessary extent, then if you direct it in the way that the Buddha described what the first jhāna is, that's how you enter the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what we spoke before, again, it's a figure of speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't really enter the first jhāna as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like waiting for you and then you do something and then you enter it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like... you dissolve yourself into it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, jhāna is a state of... jhāna is a state of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: State of being that's above the state of central being.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's sort of... That's why he said he dwells, he lives in jhāna, having developed it beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: A mode of existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a mode of existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, imagine your day-to-day life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you are... and there is a certain level of is-ness, so to speak, to the things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the is-ness of a mind who is not in jhāna, a mind not developed through wisdom, is is-ness of central domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, although you might be practicing restraint in regard to sensuality, you are still within sensual domain, which means you're still within the domain of your senses and sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything that is...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have a choice to pursue sensuality or restrain, but it's still within the sensual being.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the karmabhāva.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the existence of humans.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the human existence, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to make the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, oh, I'll replace this existence with something else, because that will kind of require you... imply that your point of view remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to dissolve the existence of kāma-bhāva, and then what you have in return is existence that's above sensuality, which is what the first jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dissolve it by understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what the Buddha described.
[SPEAKER_01]: He comes in, sets up his mindfulness, enters the jhāna, and then whether he sits, extends his arm, goes to the toilet, eats,
[SPEAKER_01]: Lays down, he's in that divine state of that jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not something you enter that absorbs you and then you kind of come out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It really becomes your mode of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what it says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having abandoned sensuality beforehand, having abandoned concern, doubt, restlessness, grief in regard to the world beforehand, you start experiencing pleasure on account of that abandonment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you start living in the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it is a pleasant abiding here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, pleasant living here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in another sutta, incidentally, Root of the Tree, it was when Anuradha, the Buddha, was encouraging him to practice jhāna, and he said, living under a root of a tree will feel like king's palace if you develop your jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't know where he is.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows exactly, but everything starts feeling
[SPEAKER_01]: Delightful, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind is completely outside of the central domain and that's where the pleasure originates from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freedom from burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, he goes on and saying...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, living under the root of a tree will feel like a king's palace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wearing rough rag, hemp type of robes will feel like Kashmir silt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fermented cow urine and feces will feel like honey and ghee and butter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... what was the other one?
[SPEAKER_01]: The rice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: The rough food he gets in Pittaburgh, we feel like the rice served by the kings and curries.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that you... like...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still the same horrible rice that he eats.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still the same rough robes that he wears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it's felt divine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like pure source of joy that you cannot even fathom, because you're still within the central being.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you withdraw yourself from the central being,
[SPEAKER_01]: Wherever, wherever you are, you're unburdened, you're free.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's again many stories in the suttas where the Buddha would be sleeping by the road on that pile of leaves, and a man walks past and says, well, whoever slept here last night must have had a rough night.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Buddha said, no, among those who sleep peacefully, I'm the foremost in sleeping peacefully.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he gives him the teaching on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, the roughness, the discomfort just
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like you're unaware of it, what's happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're aware of it, and it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, what is truly pleasant is determined whether your mind is gripped by the central being or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things just are in a different way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same things, externally, but they're lived differently now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what first jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why that's enough for arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, you can take that further as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Second jhāna, third jhāna and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the same principle of same undoing, of same withdrawal of being into a greater being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Into a more purified form of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you really want to enter jhāna, you need to first understand what your current being is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like try to escape from the current central being through attaining the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through understanding the extent of central domain, you free yourself from central domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You experience, then, joy on account of that freedom.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was thinking in terms of... so, first jhāna, or like... You might want to speak up a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the...
[SPEAKER_02]: The satipaṭṭhāna is sort of, you know, described as one sees the body within the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a kind of seeing something within a context, an outline, like a limit.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something that limits.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: A container.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what I was thinking of.
[SPEAKER_02]: That same structure applied to jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's also there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, understanding the thinking and pondering within the... Understanding the thinking and pondering, for example, within the central domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get to surmount the sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no sensuality without thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there can be thinking and pondering without sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, even your sensuality is your thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, understanding thinking and pondering within thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Realize that it doesn't matter even when you engage with sensuality, you're still within the container of your thoughts of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sensuality never leaves your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality is not in beautiful things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within you and always stays within you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's you start experiencing the beautiful things or ugly things within the framework of your central mind, which is nothing other than your central thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you learn to discern that thoughts need to be there in order for them to be central or otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you get to understand on account of central thoughts the nature of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you overcome the central thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, in the same sense, you get to understand the nature of the body as a necessary container for any sense to engage with, either for pleasure or for pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what you're exposed to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to always be within the container of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the same...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's discerning the body within the body...
[SPEAKER_01]: But that, otherwise, just means discerning the body in the right order.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, so, kāyāna-pāsanādhi,
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the body, within the body, is basically recognizing, in whatever way the body is manifested, that's within the body, it's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Knowing that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, knowing the nature of the body, knowing the necessary framework, having that peripheral
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognition of what the body is, regardless of what... of how, currently, that body is manifesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you get to see this body within the body, within the nature of the body, that kind of remains always the same, unchanging, because it's always seen on that peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, like, even... even when the Buddha encourages contemplating the aggregates,
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be again the same principle, the same answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if far or near, if there is a feeling or matter that you're experiencing, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Far or near, big or small, personal, impersonal, inside out, feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in the feeling...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever particular feeling there is, mine, others, this one, that one, that one, that one, that one, that one, feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this particular feeling is seen within the feeling being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, feeling within the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by seeing it that way, you realize, oh, it's just two points of view on the same feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you kept gratuitously assuming yourself to be somehow in between these two, like a non-defined, ambiguous center.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you were automatically regarded yourself as the owner of your feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you look at the feeling, you only get to see the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you look at the perception, you only get to see perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the bhāgī is sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the scene, let there just be the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: He could have said, in the felt, let there just be the felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, not just, oh, just pretend there's no problem with what's felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: See felt within the felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you realize that picture does not require you or your own opinion.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no room for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the body is the necessary basis for everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: This particular way in which the body is manifested, or the feelings it's enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: In jhāna, first jhāna, it's still the case that everything is contained within
[SPEAKER_02]: The body, you're still using the body as the... You can, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that body is now specifically, more specifically, manifested in the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, more like your relationship with that body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, between your point of view and the body as the means of engagement, gets more specifically around the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because once you pass the mouth, you're back onto the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're back onto the hands, groin, eyes, still mouth, nose, ears.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you start seeing the body as a whole, as a necessary container, you realize that, okay, so you are kind of... your first point of taking up your body is your mouth, since the day you came out of the womb, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not incidental that all that kind of revolves for baby, you know, putting things in its mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's its way of relating with the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that always stays, that framework stays, even when you become an adult.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you proliferate in different ways, in different ways of consuming things, so to speak, with your eyes, with your hands, but still, it's all like a representation of your relationship with your mouth, as in your relationship with your body on a more general level than the level of the specific senses you got used to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why sense-restraint is absolutely not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I keep saying that, because people say, oh, well, lay people can have jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter if you wear robes or if you wear jeans, that doesn't determine jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you cannot have is sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, lay people usually are the ones who don't restrain themselves from sensuality, because the lay life is about sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you can't have the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not because you're a layman, but because you're still not withdrawn from your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to be withdrawn from the senses, and I don't mean for a week.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be withdrawn sufficiently enough that, basically, your being gets remolded.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your state of being is now different.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a state of, oh, I'm just temporarily saying no to this in order to get jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs to be so established that, like, your saying no to senses is your normal state of being now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It requires you to make effort to go back to senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: This doesn't require any more effort, because it became your norm.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you're ready to practice the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it has been... His behavior has been thoroughly developed beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has abandoned the sensuality and the grief in regard to the world way beforehand, and experienced pleasure on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, then his mind gets composed in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's said in the first jhāna, back to what you said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, the body is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's said in that sutra, one by one, to Sariputti, Manjulnikaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, he describes the usual factors of the first jhāna, thinking, pondering, so on, and then says, contact was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, intention, attention, that was all there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and that's what Putujan's experience has as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only thing that wasn't there was sensual being.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is, my experience gets different.
[SPEAKER_01]: My experience gets purified.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still the same framework of the same experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly how Sariputta would know that there is more of this development before he gets the development.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wouldn't get the second jhāna and then say, oh, yes, there is more.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would say, oh, is there more?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, there is more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he would develop more and confirm that there is more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you realize the same framework still carries on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also, he basically was asking himself how far I can take this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you took it all the way up to the sensation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your state of being now, the framework of it stays the same in the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Minus the sensuality and pressure of the senses, organs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why everything becomes delightful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because everything is light, free, not pressuring completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literal, like, perfect equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, whichever way this goes, it's going to be pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not if I get it, but then if I don't, so there's an implicit risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: The entire domain of that kind of dependence and exposure, gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Entirely gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the Buddha described it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attention is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contact is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And perfect mindfulness is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that he went into, like, a
[SPEAKER_01]: You enter first jhāna, you enter like a transcendental state, outside of your aggregates or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's more like you fell asleep.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And drank your bowel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... How about jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to satipaṭṭhāna and jhāna, I always had taken it that, like, satipaṭṭhāna was the grounds for recollection, recollecting oneself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, and in regard to jhāna,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's that recollectedness of the body and the mind, there's not that... there can be no being scattered amongst views in regard to the experience of jhāna, for the feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, I mean, jhāna is connected to feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the sense that it's supposed to be...
[SPEAKER_00]: I remember in the Mahābhūgakaṇḍa Sūtra, the foremost feeling, the gratification of feelings, it said, is jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there are things that are felt in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, you will feel delightful on account of any feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not like, oh, feeling, normal feeling is here, and sometimes I connect my normal feeling to the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's undoing what normal feeling means for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you get closer to the feeling of jhāna, to the feeling of renunciation, to the pleasure of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, see, they said, oh, satipaṭṭhāna is the basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, satipaṭṭhāna is the basis and stays the basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't reintroduce something new then within satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still the same satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still the same principle of the same mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just instead of being anchored with seeing body within the body, you see thought within a thought, or you see mouth within the mouth, as the point of engagement with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still the same mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's still a kind of peripheral awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, same principle, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as you said before, it's not like, you know, people would think,
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhāna is the meditative experience, and then, oh, I have to be careful, because, you know, I might not be able to handle the meditative experience, or I can get it wrongly, or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're getting it wrongly, that's not the jhāna, because it's not... you can't get the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you can know it, and then, knowingly, you can obtain it, or rather, establish it at will, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, at will, you can withdraw your mind, or keep it withdrawn from the entire central being.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... and that's where jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can keep your mind withdrawn from the central being, but then end up in company, having to talk, having to engage with people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might not have the factors of the jhāna enduring at the time, but the necessary basis, the container of withdrawal from sensuality developed beforehand, from... on account of which you experience pleasure, that's still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why once your engagement stops, the seclusion is restored, the mind just goes back to jhāna, to the being in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: vihārati is the Pali word.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dwelling in jhāna literally means living in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, these days, he lives in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, these days, he lives in such and such house.
[SPEAKER_01]: These days, he lives in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: He eats, goes to toilet, sleeps in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is his mode of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't get my mode of being wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, not getting the jhāna rightly, you're already wrong, because you're already within the central domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if any meditation you pursue on account of central domain, as a replacement of what you want, of your desires, or whatever else, it's just going to be another extension of your centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Extension of... of your craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there is no sense, as Buddha described as well, like, oh, I am entering jhāna, I am in the jhāna, I am leaving jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's through overcoming that dependence of I on the senses, you establish yourself in the being of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good news, but I think there is...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you can enter jhāna, but he has to bend on his eye.
[SPEAKER_01]: He might not develop the right view in regard to his I, in regard to his I am, but he can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have that in the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually cessation of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, I am is defined by the counterpart of your senses, sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I am is the necessary by-product of sensual being.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's generated by it, as the one who is opposite of all these varieties.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when that whole sensory domain... Once you surmount the entire domain, there is no... there is no...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no space.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Symptom of I am will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sure, you can go back to sense domain unknowingly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how, like, yeah, Tuttujana can get the jhānas if he lived withdrawn from centrality for a sufficient period of time and then understood that withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he hasn't necessarily understood the nature of I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of non-ownership, for which you do need some more instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But puthujjana, who can enter jhāna, literally, practically, virtually, could probably need maybe one sentence from the Buddha, just to point to the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he would... because he's already done all the work of undoing everything unwholesome from his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, how in the sutta, sometimes... well, like bhagavad-gītā sutta we mentioned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, the Buddha told him, in scene, let there just be the scene, in heard, smell, taste, touch.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he became fully enlightened, arahant, right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think like, wow, this is so miraculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because he was living as this bhāg aesthetic, for who knows how long.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's an austere life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cover yourself with bhāg and probably eat every few days.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he fully developed his mind on account of it, to the point that he genuinely thought
[SPEAKER_01]: And you think, oh, he wasn't completely wrong, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: He had genuinely done all the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the deva, out of compassion, because he was so close already, said, actually, no, you're not, but go and visit the blessed one, and he'll tell you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, he just needed one line, one sentence, and he became fully enlightened, because everything was already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's complete withdrawal, understanding, non-ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, just he recognized it, because it was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he didn't have it there, the instruction would not have made him an arhant, would not have made him even a s
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instruction makes you discern things if those things are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means that's where the mind development and sense restraint needs to be done beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, there's nothing for you to recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he may have discovered the jhāna on his own?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, no doubt, no doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was probably quite, quite established.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas today, it seems...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, it's something I noticed when I just, like, you know... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's highly unlikely today you would discover a jhāna without Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_02]: And... but I know, also, like, if you just look at the way jhāna is taught... Oh, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: However many teachers there are, there are different ideas about what jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, as soon as you notice that, you start to think, well, they can't all be right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, something... something is omitted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It makes me think about...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, in the Buddha's time, there were other ascetics, other, I guess, teachers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did they all have different...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, because there was different definitions of Brahman for an arahant, and the Buddha had to clarify, this is what an arahant really is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Were there different definitions of what jhāna meant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there are different values, different set of goals, but if they were doing things rightly, they would have been doing it along the framework of jhānas, or those immaterial establishments of the mind, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the Buddha's previous teachings.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's structurally, if you were to develop the same principle of mindfulness, that is higher than the jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which you can only imagine, then, how much the mind of those wrong-view teachers were developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, most people today, who are familiar with suttic or not, you wouldn't be able to fade them.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, they're more developed than even monks who've been practicing the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because neither perception nor perception, it's quite a development of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a miraculous, spontaneous, mystical attainment.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, the Buddha referred to it, neither perception nor perception, the same one that then he was teaching, just with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not something different they were doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, when he became an arahant, fully enlightened, when he decided that he will teach, who shall I teach first?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, let me teach those who have the least amount of dust in their eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: People like to say and think, oh, he went to teach these previous teachers out of gratitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, they were really wrong, but out of gratitude, because they helped him in his holy search.
[SPEAKER_01]: They haven't helped him.
[SPEAKER_01]: He abandoned them, because their views were not sufficient.
[SPEAKER_01]: He found the enlightenment himself, and again, he cannot not think from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, okay, I have to teach.
[SPEAKER_01]: Teaching is a hassle.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why he didn't want to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Supreme Brahma had to ask him three times.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when he did decide to do it, he wasn't, oh, who do I feel grateful to?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it was, who'd be the quickest one to learn?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he remembered his previous teacher, because he was teaching, basically, up to the base of neither perception or perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody can get you to the point of establishing that as your mode of being, when you are in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's virtually just a step shorter than the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha could have probably... same like with Bhakti, he probably would have just told him one sentence and he would have been... That's why he said, it's such a loss for him, that he died, because if he heard me speak,
[SPEAKER_01]: His mind would have been completely liberated for good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like parinibbāna, right away.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he was so close to the goal, but then died away without hearing the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, you know, he's probably reborn in heavens and stuff, but the wrong view will eventually set in through the round of reappearances and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, okay, so who's then the next one?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well, the next one was the one that was teaching slightly lower.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, in the end, had to settle for the five disciples.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, jhānas or any of these meditative attainments, are not attainments in the sense of
[SPEAKER_01]: I got them, now I'm in them, now I'm out them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have no idea how I came to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically surmounting what you are, that's how you enter it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why you enter second jhāna by surmounting the first jhāna, which is what you are at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: You enter third jhāna by surmounting the second jhāna, which is why you... That's why you won't enter the second jhāna until you settle in the first jhāna, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're trying to surmount something you're not even familiar with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the
[SPEAKER_02]: So, can we say... so, can you say... what is it that you would bring your attention to, if you are established in seeing the body, then the body, and now you want to enter jhāna,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you've been living, withdrawn from centrality, withdrawn from any grief and concern regarding the world, as in, you've been investing effort to develop that, because it's not like you just decide, I will not be concerned about the world anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you've been investing effort to surmount that concern, to surmount that central dependence, and to stay in solitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are the necessary conditions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you start finding pleasure in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start preferring it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if you want to develop jhāna, well, you can either attempt to, for example, converging point of your thoughts towards your body, which is where the mouth is.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you associate, like, your point of view, you know, when you're thinking of something, with your head, behind your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's completely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind is not behind your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's optic nerves and brain matter is behind your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Flesh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you kind of assume you're behind the eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you took the body pretty much on the level of the mouth first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unrestrained people go much lower in terms of how far they take their body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And their being is on that level of their body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nice people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people, it's the head, to some point of view, yeah, through their point of view, and the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you start realizing that mouth hasn't been speaking for a while, the body hasn't been engaging with centrality for a while, you get to discern it as a thing being there, left alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Finally, left alone, you get to see there, oh, this is always alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when I get to interfere with it, it's only because I can...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can do so, because it's given to me as this thing that was there alone, and I can pick it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people don't have that relationship with their mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Their mouth is their thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they think, they speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: I might not say anything, but I'm still thinking it through my mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why do you need to involve the perception of your mouth when you're thinking?
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what you start attending to and basically like, like, you know, undoing something that was joined with a Velcro.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is your thoughts and your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, yeah, thoughts, mouth, still there, for an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that gratuitous connection between the two, that was the basis for your action, for your consumption, for your centrality, is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, when you think about the body through the mouth that has been left alone, not speaking for a while, you get to see the back of your head, so to speak, as sitting there, part of this lump of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are not somehow in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why that kind of practice would lead, then, to those later ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is an opening, as the Buddha said, you go in the direction of gliding the moon, flying in the air, in the divine air, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's limitless, boundless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you stop binding yourself with that which is tied to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just start looking at your mouth or observing sensations, because it's not about attending to your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about discerning the presence of the non-speaking mouth in regard to whatever you're attending to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that attention must have been rounded up and contained by the behavior purified beforehand and by the physical seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you won't be attending anything too far into the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you get to discern the peripheral of that attention, peripheral of the non-speaking mouth, more specifically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you get to stop converging your thoughts onto that physical level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you might not see a big deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might not seem like a big deal to a mind that's still living in the central being.
[SPEAKER_01]: But like, for example, the directionality of your thoughts and your mouth, it's completely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you remain bound to the sense being.
[SPEAKER_01]: You mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: When you think something, it's kind of... and then you say it, and you sort of... you... it's just this natural assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your thoughts control your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thought just controls my mouth and flows into it, and now it's out there in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mouth was always physical, thought was always mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot... they cannot, like, spill into each other's domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: One is not the master of the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: And one is not the master of the other, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize that not speaking mouth is the necessary basis for your speech.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, say one has mastered the other, it's to assume the connection between these two completely separate things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's to assume the directional connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a connection in as much with thinking and pondering, speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having thought and pondered, one breaks into speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, on the level of the mental domain, having had thoughts, speech appears on the level of physical domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you assuming the directionality means you connecting through the sense of ownership,
[SPEAKER_01]: Automatically, even if you don't necessarily think, my mouth is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is absolutely no direction between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not in the same space, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I said with the different domains, different spheres, as the Buddha would refer to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like the aggregates, as the... the... the... five different heaps.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's really not... not like... if you want... if you... if you have developed the... the... the conditions for the jhāna sufficiently, in terms of your sensory strain, withdrawal from the world, physical seclusion,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not speaking, not chatting, just adhering to silence within that framework.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about, oh, what do I attend next?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like, oh, what do I start discerning peripherally in regard to whatever I'm attending next?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is my non-speaking mouth while I'm washing the dishes, non-speaking mouth while I'm sitting quietly, non-speaking mouth while I'm looking through the window.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-speaking mouth adds a whole new layer of, like that, recognizing that separation from this lump of the body as a whole being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you stop assuming your head to be your point of view as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the non-non-speaking mouth as the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-speaking mouth stands for that which body is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of body is my hand, also no, body is my feet, body is my groin, body is my belly, everything now
[SPEAKER_01]: The body is the non-speaking mouth, the entirety of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, non-speaking mouth becomes like a gateway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a gateway for that which used to be the body we used to engage with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, anything else that you go back to the body has to be within the container, within the doorway of the non-speaking mouth.